A Guide to the William Allason Records, 1722-1847
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Allason Records, 1722-1847
Library of Virginia
13
25 reels of microfilm; 15.375 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 1912.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Glasgow, Scotland in 1731. Son of Zacharius Allason and Isbel Hall. He arrived in Virginia in 1757 as a supercargo for the Glasgow firm of Baird and Walker. Began own mercantile business at Falmouth in King George County, Virginia, later Stafford County open store in Winchester, Virginia under the direction of his brother David in 1761. Allason received and shipped goods to London, Glasgow, Liverpool, Whitehaven, Leads, Bristol and the West Indies. William Allason died in 1800. David Allason continued the operation of the Falmouth store after William's death.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, letter books, daybooks, ledgers and miscellaneous items relating to the operation of a mercantile business in Falmouth (King George County) and Winchester, Virginia by William and David Allason. The correspondence reflects the various aspects of extensive mercantile endeavor, as well as personal relationships between family members and friends. Allason corresponded with Lord Dunmore before and after Dunmore fled Virginia, and he maintained a close association with Lord Fairfax, acting as his factor, buying and selling his slaves and engaging people to collect quitrents for the Fairfax proprietary. Other correspondents include Alexander Baine, Robert Beverley, Nathaniel and Robert Burwell, Charles and Landon Carter, John Harvey, Abraham Hite, Neil Jamieson, Charles Marshall, James Mercer, General Daniel Morgan, Hugh Nelson, Mann Page, Robert Rose, David Ross, Andrew Sprowle, Col. John Taylor, Benamin Waller, John and Warner Washington, Ralph Wormeley, George Wythe and Isaac Zane.
Records identifed as Allason's during his service as agent for Baird and Walker include: daybook for a concern belonging to Baird and Walker, 1759-1769; ledger of sundry goods, 1757-1762; ledger for cargo, 1759; and ledger, 1751-1752.
Other volumes include: daybooks, 1761-1800; ledgers, 1760-1801; cash sales, 1764-1782; invoice and inventory books, 1760-1796' balances due, 1766-1792; memorandum books, 1757-1800; and tobacco books 1757- 1763, 1786-1804.
Account books of the Shenandoah store operated by David Allason include: day book, 1761-1763; and ledgers, 1761-1763. Records of his operation of the Falmouth Store include: daybooks,1775-1777, 1786-1804; and ledgers, 1783-1801.
Other volumes include: daybook and journal of private transaction, 1757-1769; daybook of Pine Forest Sawmill, 1787-1793; record of planks saved, 1787-1789; transaction at River Run mill, 1786-1787; and transaction for William Kirk's estate, 1781-1786.
Contents List
- William Allason Letter Book, 1770-1789 (Reel Misc. Reel 389)
- Letters and Papers, 1722-1760 (July) (Reel Misc. Reel 1359)
- Letters and Papers, 1760 (Aug.)-1763 (Reel Misc. Reel 1360)
- Letters and Papers, 1764-1767 (Reel Misc. Reel 1361)
- Letters and Papers, 1768-1770 (Reel Misc. Reel 1362)
- Letters and Papers, 1771(Feb.)-1773 (Reel Misc. Reel 1363)
- Letters and Papers, 1774-1782 (Reel Misc. Reel 1364)
- Letters and Papers, 1783-1785 (Reel Misc. Reel 1365)
- Letters and Papers, 1786-1788 (Reel Misc. Reel 1366)
- Letters and Papers, 1789-1791 (Reel Misc. Reel 1367)
- Letters and Papers, 1792(Mar.)-1797 (Reel Misc. Reel 1368)
- Letters and Papers, 1798-1847; Accounts and Invoices, 1775-1780 (Reel Misc. Reel 1369)
- Miscellaneous Items (Address, court Papers, Legal Documents, Agreements, Diary, Indices, Scraps) (Reel Misc. Reel 1370)
- Letter Books, 1757-1793; Day Book, 1757-1759; Ledgers, 1751-1762 (Reel Misc. Reel 1371)
- Day Books, 1761-1777 (Reel Misc. Reel 1372)
- Day Books, 1770-1780; Ledger O, 1757-1769 (Reel Misc. Reel 1373)
- Ledgers 1-3, 1769-1791 (Reel Misc. Reel 1374)
- Ledger 4, 1791-1801; Ledger A, 1760-1761; Ledger B, 1761-1762 (Reel Misc. Reel 1375)
- Ledgers C-E, 1762-1767 (Reel Misc. Reel 1376)
- Ledgers F-H, 1767-1801 (Reel Misc. Reel 1377)
- Cash Sales, 1764-1789; Invoice and Inventory Books, 1761-1796; Lists of Balances Due, 1766-1767 (Reel Misc. Reel 1378)
- List of Balances Due and Debts, 1770-1792; Memorandum Books, 1757-1792 (Reel Misc. Reel 1379)
- Memoramdum Book, 1793-1799; Tobacco Book, 1757-1796; Day Book and Journal, 1757-1769; Pine Forrest Sawmill Records, 1787-1793; River Run Mill, 1786-1787; Kirk Estate, 1781-1786; Shenandoah Store Day Book, 1761-1763 (Reel Misc. Reel 1380)
- Shenandoah Store Ledgers, 1761-1763; Falmouth Store Day Books, 1775-1804 (Reel Misc. Reel 1381)
- Falmouth Store Ledgers A-C, 1783-1801 (Reel Misc. Reel 1382)